<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at St. Pauls by Henry Maisterson ...</title>
            <author>Maisterson, Henry, d. 1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M304</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10882</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13115064</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13115064</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97738</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51573)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97738)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 427:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at St. Pauls by Henry Maisterson ...</title>
                  <author>Maisterson, Henry, d. 1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Roger Daniel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews XIII, 18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97738:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97738:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON preached at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls,</hi> By HENRY MAISTERSON Fellow of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Johns</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <p>HINC LUCEM ET POCVLA SACRA</p>
               <p>Alma Mater</p>
               <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Roger Daniel,</hi> Printer to the Univerſitie. 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97738:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97738:2"/>
            <head>To the vertuous and Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull the Lady <hi>Delves,</hi> wife to Sir <hi>Thomas Delves</hi> Knight <hi>and Baronet in Cheſhire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He world hath been dead to me of late; I wiſh I were as dead to it. It is hard to make or keep a friend in adverſity: and innocency is no protection; it rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth unto dangers. But I intend not to write ſatyres, nor to trouble your Ladyſhip with any te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious or unacceptable diſcourſe. I rather ſubmit my ſelf and cauſe to him, who is beſt able to judge: and amongſt other my worthy friends, whoſe favour hath had influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon me, I fly unto your ſelf for protection, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly intreating you to accept of my homage and ſervice, whilſt according to my ingagements I do ever remain'</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladyſhips in all hmuble obſervance, HENRY MAISTERSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:97738:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97738:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEB. 13.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>For we truſt we have a good conſcience, in all things wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to live honeſtly.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint Paul (for him wee'le ſuppoſe with all the Greek Fathers, and Saint Auguſtine, Ambroſe and Gregory among the Latine, to be the authour of this Epiſtle) know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prayer to be the golden key that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locketh the cabinet both of earthly and heavenly bleſſings, in theſe words uſeth an argument or reaſon to move the Hebrews to remember him in their prayers, and that is his confidence upon good ground that he hath a good conſcience; <hi>For we trust we have a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in all things willing to live honeſtly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words without any rack or violence offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to this diviſion: firſt, The Apoſtles confident perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>we truſt:</hi> ſecondly, the Object of it, <hi>that we have a good conſcience:</hi> thirdly, the foundation or ground upon which this edifice of truſt which towers up to heaven is built, and that is in theſe words, <hi>in all things willing to live ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly.</hi> Which words are not referred to the predicate <hi>good conſcience,</hi> as though they were a bare deſcription thereof, or a difference to diſtinguiſh what kind of good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the Apoſtle means, and to be read thus, We truſt we have a good conſcience, or a good heart, which is willing in all things to live honeſtly; or not able to fulfill the law of God as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> propounded unto Adam, but yet willing to perform Evangelicall obedience, and in all things to live honeſtly: but they are referred to the ſubject, <hi>we,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and are to be read thus, We, willing in all things to live honeſtly, truſt we have a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And ſo they note unto us not barely the object of his truſt, but the ground thereof. And then the reaſoning
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97738:4"/>ſtands thus. Firſt, To move them to pray for him, he uſeth this argument. If I have a good conſcience, then you are bound by a ſpeciall relation to pray for me, not onely as a man but as a believer: but I have a good conſcience. Therefore pray for me. Secondly, To prove his minor, he reaſons thus, He that is carefull and willing in all things to live honeſtly, he hath a good conſcience, or he may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that he hath a good conſcience: but I am willing in all things to live honeſtly. Therefore I truſt I have a good conſcience.</p>
            <p>To omit the coherence of theſe words with the former, noted unto us in the conjunction <hi>For,</hi> and to conſider them abſolutely, and in themſelves, they afford theſe three pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions: firſt, From the object of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Pauls truſt. for that is in nature before the act converſant about it, That S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul had a good conſcience: ſecondly, From the act converſant about this object, That S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul was confidently perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that he had a good conſcience: thirdly, That he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded upon this ground, becauſe he was carefull and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in all things to live honeſtly.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul had a good conſcience.</hi> For theſe words, <hi>we have a good conſcience,</hi> though read in the plurall number, are to be underſtood in the ſingular, as appeareth by the context, And I beſeech you ſomewhat more earneſtly ſo to do, that I may be reſtored to you more quickly.</p>
            <p>And here by the way, we may take notice of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Pauls modeſty (<hi>verba haec modeſtiae ſerviunt,</hi> ſaith a Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour upon this place) who, when he is to ſpeak any thing that tends to his own commendation, ſometimes uſeth the third perſon, as if he ſpake of ſome other, not of himſelf, 2. Cor. 12. ſometimes the plurall number, as aſhamed to appropriate that praiſe to himſelf, which indeed belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto him. A good example for them to think upon, whoſe vainglorious mouths are wont to trumper out their own praiſes, whilſt they forget that of the Greek Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>nothing is more lamentable then vain glory;</hi> or that of Chryſoſtome, Homil. 4. in 1. cap. Matth. <hi>Si glorificari cupis, gloriam deſpice, &amp; eris
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97738:4"/>omnibus glorioſior;</hi> but of this a word onely by the way.</p>
            <p>Now for the better underſtanding of this propoſition, it is neceſſary firſt to lay open the nature of conſcience in generall, and the ſeverall acts &amp; offices thereof: ſecondly the nature of good conſcience, and the ſeverall kinds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: thirdly, to ſhew what kind of good conſcience S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul meaneth, when he ſaith, <hi>we trust we have a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, What conſcience is. Conſcience is a part of the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall underſtanding, in all reaſonable creatures, applying their actions to ſome rule, which it conceiveth to be the Law of God, and determining either with them, or againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a part:</hi> not that the underſtanding hath parts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, it being one ſimple and undivided faculty, but by way of analogy in reſpect of divers objects and actions: And I call it a part, to ſhew that it is a naturall power, or quality created together with the ſoul, and inſeparable from it, and not an act or a habit or any thing that may be loſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>It is a part of the underſtanding,</hi> not of the will or affections. For however ſome effects there are in the will, and affections, which proceed from conſcience, as fear and terrour, which are therefore called fear and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of conſcience; yet theſe are but extrinſecall effects of conſcience, and flow not immediately from it, but from the will, as from the next and immediate cauſe, from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience remotely, in reſpect of that influence, which the underſtanding hath upon the affections.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>It is a part of the practicall underſtanding;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe converſant about action, about things done or to be done, and not about mere ſpeculation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>in all reaſonable creatures;</hi> to let you ſee the proper ſubject of conſcience. For firſt every one that hath conſcience muſt needs have reaſon. For conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth a mans life with his rule, which requireth diſcourſe. And therefore things that have no life, or having life that have not reaſon, cannot be ſaid to have conſcience. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97738:5"/>it muſt be a creature. For God the creatour of all things having no ſuperiour to impoſe a law upon him, and conſequently none that hath either right or power to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict any puniſhment, cannot be ſaid properly to have a conſcience; yet we may conceive ſome analogy betwixt ſome acts of his underſtanding, and the excuſing acts of conſcience properly ſo called. For there being in him an eternall law or rule, which he hath purpoſed from eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in all his works of creation to obſerve, his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may reflect upon the works of his hands, compare them with this rule, and judge them conformable thereunto. Thus God ſaw every thing that he had made, and behold it was exceeding good, Gen. 1. that is very artificiall, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to that idea, which God, the moſt skilfull workman, before the beginning had ſet down for himſelf to do all things by. Nor onely doth the underſtanding of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon his actions judge of that artificiall bonity which is in them, but alſo of the morall: For there being certain generall practicall notions of good and evil natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſeated in the underſtanding of God, according to which his will, the fountain of action, is moved (for his will is not, properly to ſpeak, the rule of it ſelf, but is gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by counſel) his underſtanding may reflect upon the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall acts of his will, compare them with their rule, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly judge them juſt and good, pronouncing an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving ſentence upon them, which hath much analogy and agreement with the excuſing act of conſcience proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo called.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>In all reaſonable creatures:</hi> becauſe it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that any reaſonable creature ſhould be without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, it being a part of the underſtanding; and if any ſeem to have loſt it, they have onely loſt the uſe thereof, as a mad man, or a drunken man hath loſt the uſe of reaſon, and that but for a time. For God will one day awake thoſe conſciences that were here aſleep, give mouths to thoſe that here were dumbe, ſo that they ſhall ſpeak, and never ceaſe to ſpeak, judgement, horrour, confuſion, death. For the condemning ſentence of ſuch a conſcience doth but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97738:5"/>remain like letters written with the juice of Oranges to be made legible by the fire of Gods wrath.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Applying their actions to ſome rule:</hi> Here we have the proper act of conſcience, together with the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of it. Where firſt we are to underſtand morall actions, not ſuch as are merely naturall: For theſe latter cannot be comprehended in the object of conſcience, none being ever ſo mad as to think there was either virtue or vice in them, they being the actions not of us, but of nature in us; and conſequently conſcience cannot to ſpeak properly either excuſe or accuſe us for them. Indeed it may tell us we have not done ill in them, becauſe they are neither good nor bad; but this is not properly to excuſe: for to excuſe properly is to judge that a man hath done well and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, either in a voluntary chooſing of ſome good, which he had power to have refuſed, or in a voluntary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing ſome evil, which he might have choſen.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we are to take action not ſtrictly, for exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall morall action onely; but largely, as it comprehendeth both words and thoughts. For though mans law extend no further then the outward man (<hi>Hominum leges non niſi ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternam honeſtatem requirunt, nec penetrant uſque ad inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num cor &amp; animum; ratio eſt, quia neque corda vident legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latores, nec ipſorum providentia extenditur ultra civilitatem externam)</hi> yet Gods Law, which is the rule of conſcience, is a diſcerner of the thoughts, and intents of the heart, Heb. 4.12. And therefore the Pſalmiſt calleth it a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect law converting the ſoul, Pſal. 19.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, all omiſſion of morall action is hither to be referred, whether it be <hi>directè</hi> or <hi>indirectè volita,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be a <hi>velle non agere,</hi> or a <hi>non velle agere</hi> when we may and ought. For conſcience beareth witneſſe of our omiſſion as well as of our commiſſion, of our not doing as well as of our doing.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>their actions:</hi> for the object of conſcience is our own actions. For conſcience is a power that the ſoul hath to reflect upon it ſelf, and to judge it ſelf: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not others actions, but onely ſo farre as they are
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97738:6"/>made ours, either by imputation grounded upon nature, as the ſinne of Adam; or elſe becauſe we are ſome way a cauſe of the ſinnes of others, either poſitively by furthering them, or privatively by not hindring them when we ſhould and might: And in this ſenſe that ſaying of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Gregory is true, <hi>Qui non corrigit reſecanda, committit;</hi> ſo likewiſe in the ſame ſenſe another prayeth, Lord forgive me my other mens ſinnes. But otherwiſe the ſinnes of others, which we are no wayes guiltie of, though they may be objects of our ſcience, and muſt be objects of our grief too, if we ſee and know them, yet they need not at all to trouble our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Which it conceiveth to be the law of God.</hi> Theſe words I adde for a twofold reaſon: 1. Becauſe it is not neceſſarily required to the generall nature and working of conſcience, that the thing we make conſcience of ſhould be truly commanded; it is ſufficient if conſcience appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it to be ſo. Thus ſome out of an erroneous principle make conſcience of worſhiping reliques, of adoring ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, of praying to Saints: others again oppoſe thoſe lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable ceremonies which tend to order, decency and edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in the Church, though God never required theſe things at their hands, becauſe they conceive themſelves bound thereunto by a true and reall command. 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not neceſſary that are party commanding or gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the law ſhould be truly and indeed God: it is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the generall working of conſcience, that conſcience conceive him ſo. And therefore the Heathen made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of thoſe commands which the Devil gave them in the Oracles, becauſe they thought that God ſpake by them, and in them. Virgil giveth us two examples of this in one place of his ſecond book of his Aeneid.
<q>
                  <l>Suſpenſi Eurypylum ſcitatum oracula Phoebi</l>
                  <l>Mittimus: íſque adytis haec triſtia dicta reportat,</l>
                  <l>Sanguine placaſtis ventos, &amp; virgine caesâ,</l>
                  <l>Cùm primùm Iliacas, Danai, veniſtis ad oras;</l>
                  <l>Sanguine quaerendi reditus, animâ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> litandum</l>
                  <l>Argolica: vulgi quae vox ut venit ad aures,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97738:6"/>Obſtupuere animi, gelidúſque per imacucurrit</l>
                  <l>Oſſa tremor, cui fata parent, quem poſcat Apollo.</l>
               </q> But it is neceſſary that conſcience conceive both the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to be reall, and the party commanding to be truly God, elſe it cannot bind us to obey the command, or to fear the commander. For God onely, who is creatour of conſcience, hath this priviledge to bind conſcience: And none can give this ſubjection to any, but to ſuch a one as he apprehendeth to be more then a creature. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Heathen were wont to call thoſe that were ſent to inquire of their oracles <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>vel ex</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>quaſi Dei curam gerentes,</hi> and the ſhips wherein they were ſent, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And if any object and ſay, That we are and ought to be obedient to the laws of men for conſcience ſake, Rom. 13.5. And therefore humane laws bind conſcience. I anſwer, That humane laws bind not conſcience properly by inherent virtue in themſelves, but by virtue of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall law of God, which commandeth obedience unto men; as water may burn or ſcald, not by any naturall qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity from it ſelf, but by heat received from fire: and a breach is made in conſcience, not ſimply becauſe mans law is neglected, but becauſe Gods law is broken. For, <hi>Whoſoever reſiſteth the power reſiſteth the ordinance of God,</hi> Rom. 13.2.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Determining either with them, or againſt them,</hi> which is another act of conſcience, and that is, after ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of our actions to their rule, to judge of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity or difformity thereunto.</p>
            <p>But for the better underſtanding of conſcience, conſider with me theſe diſtinct acts, and offices of conſcience.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to know and keep the law and rule which a man thinketh himſelf bound to obſerve: and conſcience in this reſpect is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To take notice of a mans actions before they are done to conſider what he is about to do, after, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and bear witneſſe of them upon occaſion, judging
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97738:7"/>of the entity and exiſtence of the action, as whether done or not done, whether with ſuch and ſuch circumſtances, or without.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To apply the action to the rule, and compare theſe two together; which act is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and from it conſcience in the Schoolmans opinion hath its name, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a knowing of the action together with the rule, or an applying of theſe two together.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, To judge of the quality of the action according to the rule, or of its agreeing or diſagreeing to the ſame; and this act is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the laſt and perfecteſt act of reaſon, or of conſcience. And becauſe every law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth two things. 1. A command of obedience: 2. A threatning of puniſhment in caſe obedience be not perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: Firſt conſcience judgeth whether the command be kept or tranſgreſſed, and conſequently whether the action for quality be good or evil, which is to excuſe or accuſe: Secondly, It judgeth of the guilt and deſert, whether the puniſhment threatned belong to the agent for this action or not, and ſo abſolveth or condemneth.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the intrinſecall acts of conſcience, which flow immediately from it; but by reaſon of that influence which the underſtanding hath upon the affections, there is a ſift act of conſcience which is to comfort and torment in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of good and bad actions paſt; to ſpurre on, to bridle and reſtrain in reſpect of good and bad actions to come: which it doth by ſtirring up thoſe foure principall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſoul, as Aquinas calleth them, <hi>viz.</hi> Joy and Sorrow, Hope and Fear; but this is but an extrinſecall effect of conſcience, as I have already ſhewed. All this is done by a practicall ſyllogiſme thus, —</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Every one that committeth murder tranſgreſſeth the law of God, and deſerveth everlaſting damnation: But,</hi> ſaith the conſcience of him that is guiltie, <hi>I have committed ſuch an act, at ſuch a time, in ſuch a place, which is murder: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have tranſgreſſed the law of God, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that committeth murder tranſgreſſeth the law of God, and deſerveth everlaſting damnation:</hi> there is the firſt act of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97738:7"/>conſcience, <hi>viz.</hi> knowledge of the command, and of the puniſhment due to the tranſgreſſion of it. <hi>But I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſuch an act, in ſuch a place, at ſuch a time;</hi> there is the ſecond act of conſcience, which is to remember and bear witneſſe of a mans actions, whether done, or not done, whether with ſuch and ſuch circumſtances or without. <hi>Which is murder:</hi> there is the third act, application of the generall knowledge to this particular action. <hi>Therefore I have tranſgrèſſed the law of God:</hi> there is accuſation; <hi>and deſerved everlaſting damnation;</hi> there is ſentence of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. And upon this ſentence in the underſtanding, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth fear and terrour in the affections. And thus much for the explication of the generall nature of conſcience, and the ſeverall acts and offices thereof.</p>
            <p>The next thing that I am to inſiſt upon, is the nature of good conſcience, and the ſeverall kinds thereof. Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thus deſcribed is either good or bad: A good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is ſuch a one as is conformable to that rule, by which it ought to be guided; A bad one, is ſuch a one as wants conformity thereunto. Both may be diſtinguiſhed according to their ſeverall ſubjects, into the good and bad conſcience of men, and of Angels.</p>
            <p>Mans conſcience (for that onely we are to ſpeak of now) is good when conformable to the will of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the Scriptures. Now becauſe the Scripture hath two parts, anſwering to the twofold eſtate of man before and ſince the fall, <hi>viz.</hi> the Law and the Goſpel, hence it cometh to paſſe that good conſcience is twofold; either Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally good, which hath that perfection which the law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth; or Evangelically good, which hath that perfection which the Goſpel accepteth unto ſalvation: Of the former ſort was the conſcience of Adam before his fall; of the latter ſort was the conſcience of Adam after his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. I might be large in ſhewing the difference, betwixt theſe two kinds of good conſcience; but I haſte. This latter may again be diſtinguiſhed into an upright conſcience, and a peaceable conſcience. An upright conſcience is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſprinkled with the blood of Chriſt, or, a conſcience
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97738:8"/>purified by faith, ſuch as is in every man that hath repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him truly of his ſinnes paſt, being for the preſent carefull and willing above all things in all things to live honeſtly.</p>
            <p>There are theſe things required to it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That it be well principled, and know in ſome good meaſure Gods commandments, accounting them the rule by which all action is to be guided. According to that Pſal. 119. verſ. 105. <hi>Thy word is a lamp unto my feet, and a light unto my paths.</hi> For as it is neceſſarily required to the generall nature and working of conſcience, that it have ſome principles which it may upon occaſion apply to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular actions; ſo it is eſſentiall to a good or an upright conſcience, that it know the true rule, and be informed with good and honeſt principles, ſo that ſo farre as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is either ignorant of the true rule, or guided by a falſe, ſo farre it is not good, but evil and corrupt: and if it be either altogether ignorant of any of the main com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, the practice of which is neceſſarily required to a Chriſtian life, as namely, that we muſt believe in Chriſt, repent of our ſinnes, and the like; or entertain any prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, which doth by direct and immediate conſequence overthrow any of theſe, it is not onely <hi>ſecundùm quid,</hi> but <hi>ſimpliciter</hi> and <hi>abſolutè mala,</hi> and falleth ſhort of that evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall goodneſſe, which is ſpoken of in my text. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe knowledge of the commandment and things to be practiced doth neceſſarily preſuppoſe knowledge of the creed and of things to be believed, it being impoſſible he ſhould not erre in principles of action, who is ignorant of the fundamentall points of faith; for example, he that thinketh there is no God, or no Chriſt, or that they regard not mens actions, to reward the good and puniſh the bad, or that is ignorant of any of theſe three propoſitions, he can never lay down this for a practicall concluſion, That God is to be ſerved, or Chriſt to be obeyed: <hi>For he that cometh to God muſt believe that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him,</hi> Heb. 11.6. hence it cometh to paſſe that a knowledge &amp; aſſent to the fundamentall points of faith, at leaſt generall and confuſed, is neceſſarily required
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97738:8"/>to integrity of conſcience, as being the foundation of that practicall knowledge, which ought to be the rule of our actions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As the ſecond act of conſcience in generall was to take notice of a mans actions, ſo it is required in the ſecond place to the nature of an upright conſcience, that out of a godly ſolicitude and fear to offend God, it obſerve a mans carriage, and take notice of his actions; that it conſider before his actions what he is about to do, that it remember and bear witneſſe afterward what he hath done, that ſo they may be applyed to their rule: And this is <hi>actio intellectûs imperaeta à voluntate.</hi> And therefore thoſe men that out of a naturall ſtrength of memory, or becauſe of ſome extraordinary impreſſion that ſome noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſinnes have made in them, remember their evil actions againſt their will, whereas they would forget them, that ſo they might be ſecure; or thoſe that out of carnall ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity take no notice of their actions, but do things raſhly, hand over head, &amp; afterward careleſſely forget what they have done, have not integrity of conſcience. I ſpeak not here of that forgetfulneſſe which proceedeth from a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in memory, but either from a cuſtome of ſinne, as thoſe that have got ſuch a habit of ſwearing that they know not when they ſwear; or from groſſe ſecurity, and want of fear of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That it apply a mans actions to the right rule impartially. And this likewiſe is <hi>actio intellectûs imperata à voluntate,</hi> and proceedeth from that godly ſolicitude, which I ſpake of before. And therefore thoſe men that apply not their actions at all to the law of God, or if they do, do it partially, groſſely favouring themſelves in their ſinnes as being loth to find them out or to part with them, have not integritie of conſcience. Nay, theſe are far from having it: For, <hi>Nemo periculoſiùs peccat, quàm qui peccata defendit,</hi> None ſinne more deſperately then thoſe that find out colours and excuſes to cover and extenuate their ſinne. And this impartiall application muſt be before and after our actions: before, that ſinne may be avoyded; after, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97738:9"/>if we have ſinned we may repent. Of the former we have a notable example in Joſeph, who when his Miſtreſſe temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to that wicked act, conſented not immediately unto her, but out of a godly ſolicitude and fear to offend God, applyeth the action to the law of God, and upon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall application finding it to be unlawfull, returneth her this anſwer, <hi>How ſhall I do this great wickedneſſe, and ſinne againſt God?</hi> Of the latter we have an example in the Prophet David, Pſalm. 119.59. <hi>I thought on my wayes, and turned my feet to thy teſtimonies.</hi> And the want of this impartiall application, as it is the cauſe of mens ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſinne without repentance, ſo it is the cauſe of their firſt fall into ſinne. <hi>Hoc nos peſſimos facit, quòd nemo vitam ſuam reſpicit,</hi> ſaith Seneca,</p>
            <p>For upon impartiall application neceſſarily followeth the fourth act of an upright conſcience, which is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the former premiſſes, to wit, a true and ſincere judgement of the action according to the commandment, at leaſt ſo farre as conſcience ſhall be inlightned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to judge; or a determination, that thoſe particular actions are good, which are indeed ſuch, and that thoſe are evil, which are in their nature evil; And this likewiſe is either before or after our actions. If this practicall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an upright conſcience be before our actions, then the effect of it is <hi>cohibere à malo, &amp; inſtigare ad bonum,</hi> to ſpurre us on to the practice of good, and to reſtrain us effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually from evil: which efficacious power the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hath upon the will and affections, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the whole man, <hi>virtute prioris actûs voluntatis,</hi> by virtue of a former complete and peremptory reſolution of the will, whereby we are reſolved to chooſe that which is good, and refuſe that which is evil, where ever we meet with it; which is that very deſire in all things to live honeſtly, which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of in my text. For that deſire which is the foundation of the Apoſtles truſt, is not a bare velleity, but a <hi>completa voluntas,</hi> which when he came to particulars put him upon action. And therefore thoſe men whoſe conſciences put them not upon the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97738:9"/>of good, nor reſtrain them effectually from evil; but ſuffer them to live in the wilfull omiſſion of good, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of evil, have not integritie of conſcience.</p>
            <p>If the action be paſt, and bad for quality, then the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an upright conſcience is to accuſe and condemne, that is, to judge the ſinne worthy damnation: And the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of this is grief and ſorrow, not onely for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we have made our ſelves obnoxious to, but for the ſin it ſelf. And therefore ſeared conſciences, which never ſmite men for their ſins; and ſecure conſciences, which do it but ſometimes, and for groſſer ſinnes; and on the other ſide wicked tormenting conſciences, which cauſe grief onely for the puniſhment and not for the offence (ſuch as was Cain's, <hi>My ſinne is greater then I can bear</hi>) theſe kinds of conſciences are not upright.</p>
            <p>But if the action paſt be good for matter and manner, then the act of conſcience ſhould be to excuſe and abſolve, that is, to pronounce it ſuch as God is well pleaſed with, and doth accept to ſalvation in Chriſt: And the effect of this is joy and comfort, ſuch as none can expreſſe, and ſuch as a carnall man cannot conceive.</p>
            <p>But becauſe no action is accepted with this kind of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, unleſſe it proceed from juſtifying faith, (<hi>For without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God to ſalvation,</hi> Heb. 11.6.) and conſequently from an upright conſcience, which is a neceſſary attendant of faith; <hi>(For faith purifieth the heart)</hi> hence it cometh to paſſe that a man cannot know that any act he doth is ſuch, unleſſe he know his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to be upright and purged by faith: which reflexed act, becauſe it neceſſarily preſuppoſeth integrity of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, (for a man cannot know that his conſcience is pure unleſſe it be ſo) therefore this is not eſſentiall to inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, but to peace of conſcience. And ſo I proceed to the ſecond kind of good conſcience, which is a peaceable conſcience.</p>
            <p>A peaceable conſcience includeth all that I have ſaid of an upright conſcience, and ſuperaddeth ſomething more. For though every peaceable conſcience be an upright con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97738:10"/>yet every upright conſcience is not alwayes able to ſpeak peace. That which it ſuperaddeth is a power to reflect upon it ſelf, and to teſtifie that it is upright, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the bloud of Chriſt. For as a man may be alive, and not know that he is alive, as a child in his mothers wombe, or a man in ſome diſtemper; ſo it is poſſible that a man may have faith and a good conſcience, and yet ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through his own weakneſſe, or ſome other extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary diſtemper or temptation, not know for the preſent that his conſcience is good. But when he is confidently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded upon good ground, that all his ſinnes are pardoned, and that his perſon is juſtified and at peace with God, then he hath not onely uprightneſſe but peace of conſcience.</p>
            <p>And ſo I have done with the ſecond thing I was to treat of, the nature of good conſcience in generall &amp; the kinds of it: I paſſe unto the third. And that is, what kind of good conſcience S.<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul meaneth when he ſaith, <hi>We truſt we have a good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, His words are not to be underſtood of a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence Legally good, or at the barre of Juſtice. For it impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a contradiction, that any ſonne of fallen Adam ſhould have ſuch a conſcience: for then he ſhould be fallen and not fallen; faln becauſe a ſon of fallen Adam, not fallen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his conſcience were legally good. For this is the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the law, <hi>Curſed is every one that abideth not in all things that are written in the book of the law to do them.</hi> it muſt therefore be underſtood of a conſcience Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally good, or at the barre of mercy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, An upright conſcience muſt be underſtood, and not a peaceable one: For though without doubt S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul had a peaceable conſcience, and theſe very words do imply as much, becauſe he was perſwaded upon good ground that his conſcience was good; yet that goodneſſe which is the object of his truſt, is goodneſſe of integrity, not of tranquillity; becauſe his truſt is built upon this grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that he was willing in all things to live honeſtly: which neceſſarily inferreth integritie but not tranquillitie of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; becauſe a man may deſire in all things to live ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97738:10"/>and yet ſometime for the preſent not have peace of conſcience.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the meaning of the propoſition, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul had an upright conſcience.</p>
            <p>This I might demonſtrate <hi>à priori,</hi> from the cauſes of integritie, as 1. The Spirit of God, the chief authour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which was not wanting to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul. 2. The word of God, the externall inſtrument, which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul was not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of. 3. Faith reſting upon the promiſes of that word, the internall inſtrument thereof, wherewith he did abound. I might likewiſe prove it <hi>à poſteriori,</hi> and ſhew you that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls whole life after his converſion, which laſted from the year of our Saviours paſſion, till the fourth year before the deſtruction of Jeruſalem (in all, about thirty ſeven years) was nothing elſe but a continuall exerciſe of an upright conſcience. And here I might ſhew you what he did for conſcience ſake, how he travelled to preach the word of God in Arabia, in Galatia and phrygia, in Syria, Aſia and Italy, in France, Spain and other countries; and that in the mean time whereas he might (as good reaſon he might) waiting on the altar have been partaker with the altar, he notwithſtanding laboured working with his hands, that he might not be burdenſome to any, 1. Cor. 4. He wronged no man, corrupted no man, defrauded no man, 2. Cor. 7. 'Tis not his own teſtimony of himſelf, but the teſtimony of the ſpirit of truth by him, and of him.</p>
            <p>I might here ſhew likewiſe what he ſuffered for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake: of the Jews five times he received fourty ſtripes ſave one, thrice he was beaten with rods, once ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; he was ſtock'd at Philippi, after again apprehended at Jeruſalem, kept priſoner two years at Caeſarea, from thence ſent bound to Rome, where he was put to death by Nero, that <hi>ſanguiſuga,</hi> that cruell and blood-thirſtie ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. But that time which is remaining bids me make haſte.</p>
            <p>Firſt, then it followeth from this propoſition, That every man is bound to get integrity of conſcience. For what S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul ſaith here of himſelf, is not proper to him, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all believers: And therefore if S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul, not as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97738:11"/>but as a believer, have an upright conſcience, it followeth <hi>ſecundùm id generis, quod est in ſpecie,</hi> That every true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever hath an upright conſcience, and that every man is bound to get one.</p>
            <p>Here likewiſe vaniſheth, like the morning dew before the ſun, the opinion of thoſe that are ſo farre from good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe themſelves, that they think there is no ſuch thing <hi>in rerum natura,</hi> in the wide world, as good conſcience, that the ſtate of regeneration is but preciſeneſſe, that true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is but an <hi>idea</hi> or an <hi>ens rationis,</hi> a Plato's common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth or a mere phanſie created in the heads of ſome fond and ſcrupulous men; That think with the Thnetopſychitae that the ſouls of men are mortall, and periſh with their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; or with the Sadduces and Simon Magus that there is no reſurrection; or with Pope Leo the tenth, that the ſtory of the birth, death and reſurrection of Chriſt is but <hi>futilis &amp; anilis fabula,</hi> an old-wifes tale, fit for nothing but to fear fools, and keep people in awe, or perhaps to be a bait to catch ſuch fiſh as St Peter fiſhed for, that have their mouths full of ſilver; or that think with the Atheiſt that there is no God, or at leaſt with Epicurus, that there is no providence, that forſooth it cannot ſtand with the majeſty of God to regard what is done in this inferiour world <hi>(ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet is ſuperis labor eſt)</hi> making God, as Tertullian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth, <hi>Otioſum &amp; inexercitum neminem in rebus humanis.</hi> But this web is not worth ſweeping down: I will not therefore honour the hereſie (pardon my miſtake, I cannot afford it ſo good a name, becauſe it is a univerſall revolt) but the Apoſtacy, the Atheiſm ſo much as to ſpend time to coufute it; I will rather turn my arguments againſt them into prayers to God for them, that if it be poſſible, the thought of their hearts may be forgiven them: for they are in the gall of bitterneſſe, and in the bond of iniquitie. And for our ſelves, let it ever be our humble prayer to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, that of all judgements he would keep from us ſpirituall judgements, blindneſſe of mind, hardneſſe of heart, a reprobate ſenſe, &amp;c. Ever praying as the Church Letany directeth us, From all falſe doctrine &amp; hereſie, from
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97738:11"/>hardneſſe of heart and contempt of thy word and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, good Lord deliver us. And, Grant we beſeech the, O Lord, that we may never make ſhipwrack of faith and good conſcience, the Ark and ſhip wherein faith is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
            <p>And ſo I proceed to a juſt cenſure of thoſe that neglect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of conſcience: and here it is no leſſe then a wonder to behold how conſcience is neglected on every ſide, which yet is not ſo wonderfull as lamentable.</p>
            <p>The covetous man ſells the integrity of his conſcience for a little red and white earth, one of the baſeſt things in the world, if we except the party that adores it, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it his God: which when he hath got, the Cheſt he putetth it into may be ſaid to poſſeſſe it as truly as he. For it keepeth it <hi>(clauſum poſſidet arca Jovem)</hi> and he doth no more: For he is afraid to uſe it. <hi>Quaerit, &amp; inventis miſer abſtinet, &amp; timet uti.</hi> The ambitious man ſelleth it for the thing called Honour which can neither be got nor enjoyed without labour and travail. <hi>Fructus honos oneris, fructus honoris onus.</hi> And therefore the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifieth <hi>honour</hi> cometh <hi>à radice</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies <hi>ponderoſum eſſe,</hi> to be heavy or burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. To which we may apply that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Auguſtine, <hi>Qui te amat, non te cognoſcit; qui te contemnunt, ipſi te intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt.</hi> The envious man, for a little <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or a ſhort rejoycing at the miſery of his brethren. The vain glorious man, for the breath of the multitude, which he can enjoy no longer then he is every mans ſervant, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis ſinguliſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſervit ſervus gloriae.</hi> The adulterer, for a momentany dalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which perhaps leaveth rottenneſſe behind it in his bones.</p>
            <p>The proud perſon that doteth upon apparell, the thing that blazons mans downfall and the devils conqueſt, puts of integrity of conſcience as a wear out of faſhion, to put on a phantaſtick garment, which may force the beholders into wonder, not ſo much at the ſtrangeneſſe of the unwon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted habit as the monſtrous folly of the party that wears it. Nazianzen affords theſe no better a name then ſilk-wormes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97738:12"/>or butterflies; and doubtleſſe ſuch ridiculous creatures they are in the eyes of God, and his Saints and Angels, who va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue not the adorning of the outward man, but the comely ornament of an upright and undefiled conſcience.</p>
            <p>The beaſtly intemperate drunkard and glutton (par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the weakneſſe of the expreſſion) chops away the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of his conſcience for a ſinne which turnes men into ſwine, with ſuch deviliſh charms, that they would not leave their bruitiſh nature for their former reaſon; or if you will, for a pleaſure ſcarce two fingers long, <hi>quae non durat niſi quantum durat tranſitus ille per gulam,</hi> which continues but whilſt the meat paſſeth from mouth to ſtomach; and that too is but an anteambulo to uſher in a thouſand pains and diſtempers. Such pleaſures as theſe are but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>deceitfull miſtreſſes,</hi> or rather <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>bitter-ſweet delights,</hi> or, <hi>pleaſures mixt with pain:</hi> Of which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Cyprian excellently, <hi>Voluptatem viciſſe voluptas eſt maxima,</hi> The greateſt pleaſure, is to overcome theſe pleaſures.</p>
            <p>The ſacrilegious Church-robber puts out the integrity of his conſcience, by putting forth his unhallowed hand to purloyn that which is ſacred, and to eat the forbidden fruit, upon which God hath ſet a <hi>noli me tangere.</hi> This ſtole a good conſcience from Adam, and caſt him out of para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, whilſt he robbed God of his forbidden fruit; and I fear it hath deprived many a ſonne of Adam, not onely of the integrity of his conſcience, but of his earthly inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>Ile adde but one inſtance more, and that is thoſe reſtleſſe ſpirits, whoſe cheif ſtudy it is, without call from God, by wicked contrivement and ſinfull practices to enervate and weaken that wholeſome eſtabliſhed government, which through the provident care of vertuous kings and religious parliaments hath a longe time flouriſhed and ſtill doth flouriſh (thanks be to God and a good King) both in Church and ſtate. Theſe ſell integrity of conſcience for ſwarms of diſcontented thoughts, whereby they do but turn themſelves into hives of unnumbred cares, ſorrows
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97738:12"/>and paſſions, make themſelves in an eſpeciall manner the outlawryes of heaven, and ſometimes procure their own juſt and deſerved puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Thus I have run through ſome ſinnes no leſſe dangerous then common: it would not be hard, were it not too tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to do the like in all profeſſions; but I'le onely inſtance in one, without private ſpleen to place or perſon, and that is the unconſcionable tradeſman: And for the reſt, becauſe time will not permit, I leave their own conſciences to make the application.</p>
            <p>A man would bleſſe himſelf to think what a world of myſteries are found out in every trade, what tricking and counterfeſance to delude the ſenſe, what intricate devices of ſophiſtry &amp; diſſimulation, what lying, equivocating, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſwearing and forſwearing, and all this for the getting of a little mony, which when it is lawfully got is but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Luke 16.9. that is, not Mamon about which the ſonnes of men uſe to be unrighteous, as ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the words; but <hi>Mamona fallax,</hi> ſo Beza, that is, deceivable and uncertain riches, when compaſſed by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full means, and no fit objects for us to truſt upon, being ſuch things as are but got out of the bowels of the earth, and which they that have them are forced many times (like Euclio in Plautus) to hide there again. And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding how ordinary is it with men, for the getting of this traſh, to tranſgreſſe both againſt religion and reaſon, as if they hoped that after this life there were nothing to be hoped for; and to violate the laws of juſtice in their une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall weights and meaſures, in their abuſing ignorant and unskilfull chapmen, whereas commutative juſtice obſerves <hi>proportionem arithmeticam,</hi> an arithmeticall proportion, which is immutably one and the ſame in reſpect of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of what quality ſoever. Such as theſe ſell integrity of conſcience for gain, and yet gain nothing by that bargain but the loſſe of their ſouls, whilſt with the golden book they ſwallow down the worm of conſcience, and barter away their own eternall happineſſe for very trifles, which, if they did but like the good merchant buy that pearl our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97738:13"/>Saviour ſpeaks of, Matth. 13. ſhould as farre as were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient as a mantiſſa or an overplus be caſt in at their bargain. But if any ſhall make profeſſion of religion profits ſtirrup to get up by, and bait craft with humility, rough caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his countenance as if by an hypocriticall monopoly he had ingroſt all honeſty and integrity of conſcience, that he may the more eaſily deceive, his caſe is farre worſe then the former. Is religion grown now to be an art of decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving? or doth he deſerve the name of Chriſtian, whoſe chief ſtudy it is <hi>ſcitè mentiri, id eſt, mentiri ut lucro ſit, nec tamen poſsis deprehendi,</hi> as Eraſmus ſpeaketh. Nay I muſt tell him heis ſtark nought as well as the former, and doubleth his fault by ſeeming good. And if any notwithſtanding this perſwaſion ſhall ſtill perſiſt, either in this or in any other ſinfull way, let them go on to pleaſe themſelves, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe their God in their over greedy purſuit of unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vanitie. Let me onely have an upright conſcience for my portion, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as Iſocrates of virtue; and let me never want it till I envy them.</p>
            <p>And for our ſelves, if we delight not to weave the web of our future wo, let it be our chiefeſt care to get, and having got, to keep integritie of conſcience. Ile adde but two motives to move you thereunto; A good conſcience will be your beſt friend, and a bad conſcience will be your worſt enemy.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A bad conſcience will be your worſt enemy. It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives us for the preſent of union with God, of communion with Chriſt, of intereſt in his promiſes, of protection of his angels, and of title to heaven; and when God ſhall awake it and arm it againſt us, it will ſting us with ſuch torments, as I pray God we may rather know by relation then expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. An ancient Father calls this horrour of conſcience, <hi>primitias infernalis flammae;</hi> and I may call it a walking hell. For our Saviour himſelf ſeemeth to intimate that the rack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of a ſelf-accuſing conſcience are the greateſt part of their torments that are condemned to that dungeon where darkeſſen putteth on her blackeſt garment.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97738:13"/>2. A good conſcience will be our beſt friend. It will be our moſt plain-dealing friend, our faſteſt friend, and our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenteſt friend.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our moſt plain-dealing friend. Some are flattering friends and will not ſpeak and inform men of their miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, but rather make them believe that all their vices are virtues, and all their dusky actions chryſtalline. <hi>Nimis ſciti ſycophantae,</hi> to uſe Plautus his phraſe, men that live altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of themſelves ſtudying other mens humours. Like Gnatho in Terence, <hi>Quicquid dicunt laudo, id rurſum ſi ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, laudo id quoque: negat quis? nego; art? aio.</hi> Others again are fearfull friends, and dare not ſpeak leſt they incurre diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, and indeed all men naturally are diſpleaſed with thoſe that inform them of their miſdoings, eſpecially thoſe that are great, and unwonted to be croſt in their deſires. Theſe many times reward good counſel with ill turns, and account reall injuries the juſt recompence of wholſome reproof: witneſſe John the Baptiſt, who loſt his head for tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Herod it was not lawfull for him to keep his brothers wife. Witneſſe Caliſthenes, who loſt his life, not for betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Alexander to others, but becauſe he would not betray Alexander to himſelf, and account him worthy of divine worſhip, as all his deteſtable flatterers did. Witneſſe S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> paul in my text, who, if S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chryſoſtoms teſtimony be true in his firſt book <hi>adverſùs vituperatores vitae monaſticae,</hi> was ſlain by Nero for diſwading an harlot of his from proſtituting her ſelf to his ungodly deſires. The obſervation of which pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of great ones cauſed a witty ſpeach to fall from a famous man of our times, that whoſoever ſhould follow truth too near the heels it might happily ſtrike out his teeth. And in this regard the moſt are affraid to admoniſh, eſpecially great ones when they do amiſſe, and all generally are ſhie and loth to ſpeak truth. But now a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence neither deſireth to flatter us, nor feareth to tell us the truth, be we what we will or can be however it be taken.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is our faſteſt friend. The relation betwixt man and wife is a near relation; but the relation betwixt a man and his conſcience is nearer. Conſcience lieth with us,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97738:14"/>ſits with us, rides with us; a man may as ſoone fly from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as from his conſcience. Jonathan never adhered ſo to David, though the text ſaith, <hi>he loved him, as his own ſoul.</hi> Niſus never ſtuck ſo cloſe to Euryalus, though he deſired by his own death to ranſome the others life, <hi>Me, me, adſum qui feci, in me convertite ferrum, &amp;c.</hi> Nor This be to her beloved Pyramus, though ſhe endevoured to accompany him after death, <hi>Quique, à me morte revelli Heu ſolâ peteras: poteris nec morte revelli.</hi> I ſay none of theſe did ſo adhere to other, as good conſcience will to us; when riches, when friends when parents, when life and breath forſake us, good conſcience can, yea cannot chooſe but cleave unto us:</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is our potenteſt friend. Good conſcience is the darling of the Almighty, which if we do but continue faithfull in her ſervice will crown us with peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence here, and hereafter with eternall happineſſe. For though theſe two may happily be ſevered for ſome time, as I have already ſhewed, yet the fruit of conſtancy in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is peace even in this life. And therefore S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine calls them <hi>duas ſorores;</hi> &amp; he that is conſtant in his love to the one, ſhall be ſure to be beloved of the other. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity and peace, like Martha and Mary, dwell under one roof. O ſweet and bleſſed name of peace, the beauty of heaven, the deſire of earth, the joy of angels, that every good, and every thing, that all that man delights in! Who but a man poſſeſt with frenzie would not labour for thee? who but a cruell tyrant againſt his own ſoul can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with any other reward but thee? <hi>ô ſelix conſcientia jucun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditas</hi> (cries out holy Auguſtine, as in an extaſy) <hi>paradiſus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiarum, palatium Dei, thalamus Chriſti, habitaculum Spiritûs ſancti: Tu in terra ad huc es, &amp; in caelis habitas.</hi> O happy, thrice happy peace of conſcience; thou art yet on earth, and yet thou dwelleſt in heaven, or rather thou changeſt the earth thou art in, into heaven, what have not the bleſſed Saints done for thee? what have not the crowned martyrs ſuffered with thee? Bleſſed is that ſoul which poſſeſſeth the, or rather which thou poſſeſſeſt. For it hath in deepeſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row height of joy, proſperity in adverſity, liberty in capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97738:14"/>and life in death. 'Tis an inſtrument that 's ſweetly tuned, 'tis an angell clad in fleſh, 'tis a mint of golden thoughts, 'tis a world of joy and concord, where there is nothing but halcyon and ſummer dayes of peace. Happy is the man that is in ſuch a caſe, yea bleſſed is he that hath peace of conſcience for his portion.</p>
            <p>And now me thinkes it is labour in vain for Coſmogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers to ſpend themſelves in finding out the place where paradiſe was ſeated. It was not the whole earth, as ſome conceive; nor a place mounted higher then the middle region of the air, as others; nor betwixt the tropicks in the torrid zone under the equinoctiall; nor in the countrey of Eden, or in the parting of the two regions Aſſyria and Babylonia: It is not in your pleaſant gardens, though they perhaps may excell thoſe of Alcinous mentioned by Homer, when in the pride of their ſpring they are beſpangled with all choyſe of eye-pleaſing flowers; nor in your orchards of delight, ſurpaſſing the Elyſian fields, adorned with variety of beautifull walks, &amp; thoſe ſhaded with the green canopy of every pleaſant and fruitfull tree: It is not in your glorious wardrobes, though they perhaps be fild with garments of ſilk, and of broydered work, of fine linen corall and pearl: It is not upon your couches of Ivory, nor in venereous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces upon beds of down, deckt with coverings of tapiſtry, and of carved work, perfumed with myrrhe, aloes, and ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon. It is not on your richly furniſhed tables, though they abounded with all variety of creatures that earth, and ſea, and air can afford: But if you will needs know where to find out this place of bliſſe, believe me (for you may) it ever was, and is, and there onely is, where there is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity and peace of conſcience.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, good conſcience, if we continue faithfull in her ſervice, will crown us with eternall happineſſe. What pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments hath ſhe procured at the mercifull hands of God, for all thoſe that have lived and dyed in her ſervice? How doth joy now triumph in the eyes, and comfort lodge in the hearts of all thoſe, that whilſt they were here upon earth were carefull with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul to keep a conſciencevoyd of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97738:15"/>offence toward God, and toward men. How muſt their ſouls needs be full of angels pleaſures, and ſwell with over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing delights, how do they bury the miſeries that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell them here, in the triumph of that conqueſt which they have obtained over the enemies of their ſalvation? Though my ſpeech ſhould be as endleſſe, as their joyes, yet would it come too ſhort of a full expreſſion. For the excellency of happineſſe can neither come out of the ſpeaker by rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor enter into the hearer by apprehenſion, yet I'le tell you what S. Auguſtine ſaith of it, in the 22. Chap. of his meditation. <hi>O tu vita quam praeparavit Deus iis qui diligunt eum: vita vitalis, vita beata, vita tranquilla, vita ſecura, vita pulchra, vita munda, vita caſta, vita ignara mortis, neſcia triſtitiae, &amp;c. Quantò plùs valeo mecum conſiderare, tantò plùs amore tui langueo.</hi> And no marvel, holy Auguſtine. For thoſe that enjoy this life behold to their unſpeakable comfort the hoſt royall of the bleſſed Angels, the holy ſpirits of Saints departed, the noble army of martyrs, which now ſhine much brighter then thoſe flames, which here put a period to their tranſitory lives, the glorious company of the Apoſtles, the goodly fellowſhip of the prophets, and which is more, the moſt ſacred humility of our Saviour, and his comely face, fairer then the ſonnes of men, clearer then the ſun, and that which infinitely tranſcends what is or can be ſaid, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious preſence of him, who is all in all; a power ineffable, a vertue infinite, a light by abundant clarity inviſible. I will therefore conclude with S: Auguſtines exclamation, <hi>O ergò felix ju ounditas, &amp; jucunda felicitas ſanctos videre, cum ſanctis eſſe, &amp; ſanctum eſſe; Deum videre, &amp; Deum in aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num habere, &amp; ultrá.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God of his infinite mercy teach our conſciences now whilſt we live to nature, to dy to ſinne, that ſo when we dy to nature we may live with him in this bliſſefull life of glory.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97738:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
